Guide to the Michael Harrington Papers TAM.209
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Michael Harrington Papers
1946-1990
1960-1989
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Harrington, Michael, 1928-1989
Harrington, Stephanie
TAM.209
9 Linear Feet (11 boxes)
Michael Harrington (1928-1989) was a U.S. socialist, editor, writer, founder and leader of Democratic Socialists of America (U.S. affiliate to the Socialist International), and political leader best known for his book The Other America: Poverty in the United States(1962). These papers include his notebooks, correspondence, and documentation of his various political and journalistic endeavors.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open for with no restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Stephanie Harrington in 1998. The accession number associated with this gift is 1999.004.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Reading Notebooks; II. Writings, Correspondence, & Other Activities; III. Addendum (Reading Notebooks)
Folders are arranged alphabetically within each series.
Historical/Biographical Note
Michael Harrington (1928-1989), a U.S. socialist writer and political leader, best known as the author of The Other America: Poverty in the United States(1962), and as the founder and leader of Democratic Socialists of America, the U.S. affiliate to the Socialist International, was born in St. Louis, received a Jesuit secondary education, graduated from Holy Cross College in 1947 and, after a brief interval at Yale Law School, received a MA degree in English from the University of Chicago in 1949, then moved to New York City.
From 1951-53 he was a volunteer at the radical Catholic Worker house on New York's Lower East Side, and was associate editor of its newspaper, also called the Catholic Worker. Leaving Catholicism, he first became organizational director of the Workers Defense League in 1953, joined the Socialist Party, and shortly became the leader of the SP's Young People's Socialist League. Coming under the influence of the (not quite yet) post-Trotskyist Max Shachtman, whose anti-Communism and grand political strategy, known as realignment (i.e., seeking to employ a leftist-influenced organized labor movement as the leading force in reorienting the Democratic Party towards socialism) became and remained in one form or another the cornerstones of Harrington's political outlook, Harrington led the New York YPSL into Shachtman's Independent Socialist League in 1954, and served as YPSL national chair until the 1958 dissolution of the ISL and its members' return to the Socialist Party, and from 1960-62 edited New America, the SP paper.
From 1954 through 1962, Harrington worked as a researcher for the Fund for the Republic, notably on its study of blacklisting in the film industry, and wrote for liberal and left journals of opinion such as Dissent. A 1957 Commentary article on poverty grew into The Other America, which made Harrington a national figure, and which was widely credited with influencing the development of the so-called War on Poverty and related local programs during the Kennedy and Johnson presidencies. The Port Huron Statement, also published in 1962 by the Students for a Democratic Society, originally a project of the SP-associated League for Industrial Democracy, for whom Harrington served as liaison to SDS (he would become LID head in 1964), was sharply criticized by Harrington for being insufficiently anti-Communist. This marked the beginning of a decade of often sharp disagreement with the New Left, most importantly on the related issue of the Vietnam War. While Harrington's Realignment Caucus within the SP (he was elected SP chair in 1968) opposed the war, it did not support unconditional withdrawal. In 1971 Harrington formed the Coalition Caucus, which backed the 1972 presidential candidacy of George McGovern in opposition to the pro-war SP majority, then left the SP to found (in February 1973) the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee, which merged, in 1982, with the New American Movement, an organization of New Left veterans, to form the Democratic Socialists of America.
In 1972 Harrington became a professor of political science at Queens College in New York City, played a leading role during the 1980s in the drafting of the Socialist International's New Declaration of Principles, and continued to write, lecture and travel widely until his death from cancer in 1989. Among his many books were two autobiographical works, Taking Sides: The Education of a Militant Mind(1985) and The Long-Distance Runner: An Autobiography(1987), The New American Poverty(1984), The Politics at God's Funeral: The Spiritual Crisis of Western Civilization(1985), and Socialism: Past and Future(1989). See also the selected bibliography, below, preceding the box and folder list.
Selected Bibliography
1959: Labor in a Free Society(Berkeley, University of California Press), 186 p.
1960: Democracy and Public Review: An Analysis of the UAW Public Review Board/ by Jack Stieber, Walter E. Obrerer, Michael Harrington (Santa Barbara, CA: Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions), 64 p.
1962: The Other America: Poverty in the United States(New York, Macmillan), 191 p.
1962: The Retail Clerks(New York, Wiley), 99 p.
1965: The Accidental Century(New York: Macmillan), 322 p.
1967: American Power in the Twentieth Century(New York: League for Industrial Democracy), 55 p.
1968: Toward a Democratic Left: A Radical Program for a New Majority(New York, Macmillan), 314 p.
1972: Socialism(New York, Saturday Review Press), 436 p.
1972: The Seventies: Problems and Proposals/ edited by Irving Howe and Michael Harrington (New York: Harper & Row), 519 p.
1973: Fragments of the Century(New York, Saturday Review Press), 246 p.
1976: The Twilight of Capitalism(New York: Simon and Schuster), 446 p.
1977: The Vast Majority: A Journey to the World's Poor(New York: Simon and Schuster), 281 p.
1980: Decade of Decision: The Crisis of the American System(New York: Simon and Schuster), 354 p.
1981: The Next America: The Decline and Rise of the United States(New York: Holt, Rinehart, and Winston), 154 p.
1981: Unfinished Democracy: The American Political System/ Harrell R. Rodgers, Jr., Michael Harrington (Glenview, Ill.: Scott, Foresman, 1981), 625 p.
1984: The New American Poverty(New York: Holt, Rinehart, and Winston), 271 p.
1985: The Politics at God's Funeral: The Spiritual Crisis of Western Civilization(New York, N.Y., U.S.A.: Penguin Books), 308 p.
1985: Taking Sides: The Education of a Militant Mind(New York: Holt, Rinehart, and Winston), 278 p.
1987: The Next Left: The History of a Future(New York: H. Holt), 197 p.
1988: The Long-Distance Runner: An Autobiography(New York: Holt), 260 p.
1989: Socialism: Past and Future(New York: Arcade), 320 p.
See also: Isserman, Maurice, The Other American: The Life of Michael Harrington(New York: Public Affairs, 2000), 449 p.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Democratic Socialists of America Records (TAM 105)
Democratic Socialists of America Audiocassettes (OH 058)
Michael Harrington - DSA Audiotapes (OH 048)
Maurice Isserman Research Files for The Other American: The Life of Michael Harrington (TAM 239)
Scope and Content Note
The notebooks (which are undated) are arranged alphabetically. They comprise more than three-fourths of the collection, and contain Harrington's handwritten notes on his readings from the 1960s through the 1980s, principally of the works of Marx, Hegel, Continental and ancient Greek philosophy, current economic and social conditions, political economy, political theory, theology, and American and European literature. Harrington read works in their original languages, and the sometimes multi-lingual notes reflect Harrington's facility with French, German, Greek and Latin. About one-third of the often multi-volume notebooks are labeled with abbreviated titles for several of Harrington's published books, notably Toward a Democratic Left(1968), Twilight of Capitalism(1976), and Decade of Decision(1980), while the remainder are labeled with broad topical terms or the names of prominent authors. Of interest for Harrington's early years in New York are the notebooks titled "Me - Boheme," and "Village."
Series two, arranged alphabetically by topic, contains typescripts for unpublished and published articles, book reviews, lectures, speeches, and for a debate with Carl Gershman; three audio recordings of lectures on Marxism; typescripts for The New American Poverty (1984) and Socialism, Past and Future (partial, 1989); three oral history interview transcripts (1965, 1988); documents from and unpublished Harrington reports on several Socialist International leadership meetings, including one discussing the Palestine Liberation Organization (1979); additional reading notes; publishing and miscellaneous correspondence; clippings; materials relating to Harrington's teaching career; U.S. Senate testimony (1987); and an invitation to the funeral of Robert F. Kennedy.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Notebooks; Typescripts; Correspondence.; Socialists -- United States.; Harrington, Michael, 1928-1989; Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (U.S.); Gershman, Carl; Munaẓẓamat al-Taḥrīr al-Filasṭīnīyah; Socialist International (1951- ); Democratic Socialists of America; Harrington, Stephanie
- Series I. Notebooks
  - Agency France Presse (3 books), undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - CAP Forum Debate, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - DEC Decade of Decision(11 books), undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - EVR "70, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Greek Language Notebooks (4 books), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Henri Saint Simon (2 books), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Iliad, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - India (2 books), undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - LH3 Intro, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Lukacs, Gyorgy (3 books), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Marx, Karl (early), undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Marx (19 books), undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Marx Das Kapital(11 books), undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Me: Boheme, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Me I: Village, SDS, ED of MH, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Misc. (2 books), undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Neo-Con (2 books), undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Notes of a LDR [ Long Distance Runner], undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "OAR", undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Philosophy Section 1 (16 books), undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Philosophy Section 2 (2 books), undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Philosophy Section 3 (7 books), undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Philosophy Section 4 (4 books), undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Philosophy Section 5 (2 books), undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Philosophy Section 6 (Untitled Misc.) (2 books), undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Playing Delta", undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - SOC ["Socialism?"] (11 books), undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Soc Crisis ["Crisis of Socialism?"] (8 books), undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Soc Hist (3 books), undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Soc Int"l, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - TDL [ Toward a Democratic Left] (12 of 13 books), undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - TW [ Twilight of Capitalism] (6 of 7 books), undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - TWC [ Twilight of Capitalism], undated (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - USS ("US Socialism") (3 books), undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Untitled Misc. (3 books), undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Untitled (Theology), undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - WC [Working Class], undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - "Whither A." (Loose), undated (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Legal Sized Notebooks (3 large notebooks), undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Series II: Writings & Other Activities
  - Against Unemployment (Talk, Dublin 24 pp), Jan 1, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Book Review: Marx"s Social Critique of Culture, by Louis Dupre, ca.1983 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - City University of New York (CUNY), 1971-1989 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Clippings re Michael Harrington, 1964, 1977, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - "Conservative Trend" Untitled Lecture - Typescript 13pp, ca.1979 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1948, 1957-1958, 1976-1991 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence: Guggenheim Foundation, 1982-1983 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence: Publishers, 1970, 1982-1989 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence: Simon and Schuster, Inc., 1974-1982 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - "Crisis of Collective Bargaining" (Untitled typescript 36pp and notes), ca.1960s (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - "Danger from the Right" (Untitled book-length typescript), ca.1964 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Economic Article or Pamphlet for Irving (not Howe), 1982 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - The Economic Opportunity Act (Address 31pp), 1964 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Future Present (Typescript 36pp), undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Gershman, Carl: Confidential Memorandum re: Socialist International Bureau Meeting 15-16 Oct. 1977, ca.1977 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Gershman, Carl: Debate with Michael Harrington (CG Presentation), 1980 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Harrington, Michael: Interview with John Cogley, by Hela Kaufman at the Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions (15pp), 1965 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Harrington, Michael: Oral History Telephone Interview Typescript, 35pp (William Chafe, Interviewer), Nov 26, 1988 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Harrington, Michael: Untitled Lecture (re: Justice) Transcript 22pp, Sep 20, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Hegel: Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Hegel: Philosophy of Right, Typed Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Holy Cross College: The Tomahawk(student newspaper), 1946 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - The Individualistic Welfare State, undated (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Isserman, Maurice: "Michael Harrington: Another American" (Paper given at Harvard - Incomplete Typescript), Oct 15, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Kennedy, Robert F.: Funeral Invitation, Jun 1, 1968 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - Labor Movement - Typed Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - Larkin, James: Memorial Lecture, Jan 27, 1989 (Box 7, Folder 27)
  - League for Industrial Democracy: Untitled Talk by MH (Transcript 48pp), 1980 (Box 7, Folder 28)
  - "The Magnificent Decadence:" (Unpublished Typescript), undated (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - "Michael Harrington Lecture" (at OSU - Oxford Student Union - Transcript 47 pp), 1980s (Box 7, Folder 30)
  - New American Poverty Untitled Book-length Typescript, undated (Box 7, Folder 31)
  - New Poverty in America - Typed Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 32)
  - The Perils of a Dead Economy (Published Article: pp 417-426), 1985 (Box 7, Folder 33)
  - Philosophy: Typed Notes, Misc., undated (Box 7, Folder 34)
  - Political Theory Typed Notes (The "Classics"), undated (Box 7, Folder 35)
  - Poverty - Typed Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 36)
  - Religion - Typed Notes, undated (Box 7, Folder 37)
  - "Soc Crisis" Typed Notes (re: Luxemburg and Trotsky), undated (Box 7, Folder 38)
  - Socialism Past and Future: Chapter Four; The End of Socialism, undated (Box 7, Folder 39)
  - Socialism Past and Future: Introduction by Arthur Lipow - Typescript, undated (Box 7, Folder 40)
  - Socialism Past and Future Reviews, 1965, 1989-1990 (Box 7, Folder 41)
  - Socialist International and PLO, Talk on, ca.1979 (Box 7, Folder 42)
  - Socialist International Bureau Meeting, Lisbon, Oct 30, 1979-Oct 31, 1979 (Box 7, Folder 43)
  - Socialist International: Untitled Typescript on February Leader's Conference, Vienna, ca.1980 (Box 7, Folder 44)
  - Structures of Misery: The New American Poverty(Typescript), undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - U.S. Senate, Testimony, Jan 13, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Voices from the Catholic Worker(1993) MH Interview Transcript, Jul 7, 1988 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Washington, D.C. Protest March: Untitled Speech for, ca.1967 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - "We are Socialists" Typescript, undated, 1980-1981 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - "The Working People of North America" Typescript, undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - "Working People of North America," The Beginnings, undated (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Marxism III "The Communist Manifesto" New York City Y.P.S.L. Parts 1-3, 1969 March 16 (Box 11, Reel 2)
  - Marxism IV "Political Perspectives" New York City Y.P.S.L. Parts 1-3, 1969 March 9 and 1969 March 23 (Box 11, Reel 4, Reel 6, Reel 5)
  - Video of Michael Harrington, rolls 1-6, by Cambridge Documentary Films. master and dub., 1988-05-02 (Box Shared Tamiment 013, Cassette 12-13)
  - Videotapes: Michael Harrington, Democracy '76, Democratic National Convention, produced by Video Factory, Port Jefferson, NY; 2 unmarked, 1976, undated (Box Shared Tamiment 013)
- Series III. Addendum: Reading Notebooks
  - Accidental Century(10 books), undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Decadence (book II), undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Europe, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - FP, undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Hegel - Dialectics/Logic (2 books), undated (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Marx (Books I, II, III), undated (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Marx (Books I, II, III, VII, XII, XVII), undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Marx: Misc. Texts (Books I, II, III), undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous (2 books), undated (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Oil, undated (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Twilight of Capitalism(9 books), undated (Box 10, Folder 1)